Finding Aid for College of Engineering (University of Michigan) records 1860-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Dean's Files, 1904-1991
  - Deans Office Files, circa 1945-1990
    - Deans' Administrative Files
      - Industrial Engineering Curriculum, 1951-1968; 2 folders (Box 52)
      - Industrial Engineering Department, 1969-1971
        - Memoranda, 1972-1977 (Box 52)
      - Industrial Program Correspondence, 1954-1955; 3 folders (Box 52)
      - Industry Committee
        - Correspondence, 1955-1971; 4 folders (Box 52)
        - Engineering Laboratories, undated (Box 52)
        - General Information, 1956-1962 (Box 52)
        - Meeting Plans, 1954 (Box 52)
        - Subcommittee #1, 1968-1971 (Box 52)
      - Industry Program (Box 53)
        - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 53)
        - General Information, 1952-1957 (Box 53)
        - Meeting Announcements and Minutes, 1965-1967 (Box 53)
        - Summer Conference, 1952-1970 (Box 53)
      - Institute of Science and Technology, 1957-1966; 4 folders (Box 53)
      - International Cooperation Administration-Waseda University Project, 1955-1959 (Box 53)
      - International Nickel Co., Inc., 1952-1960 (Box 53)
      - Instructional Television, 1953-1985; 2 folders (Box 53)
      - Jackson Building Collapse, 1956-1957 (Box 53)
      - JESSI (Junior Engineers and Scientists Summer Institute), 1963-1965 (Box 53)
      - Korea University, 1967-1968 (Box 53)
      - Large Laboratory Operations, 1969 (Box 53)
      - Literature, Science and the Arts, College of, 1950-1968; 2 folders (Box 53)
      - North Campus
        - Buildings
          - General, 1955-1959 (Box 53)
          - Report of Space Study and Recommendations, 1959 (Box 53)
        - Development Plans, 1958 (Box 54)
        - Engineering Laboratories Committee, 1956-1958 (Box 54)
        - Library, 1965 (Box 54)
        - Planning Committee, 1956-1966; 3 folders
          - Projected Departmental Space Needs, 1965-1966 (Box 54)
          - Reports, 1956 (Box 54)
          - Subcommittee Minutes, 1956-1959 (Box 54)
        - Shop Facilities, 1955 (Box 54)
      - Organization Information, 1970-1980 (Box 54)
      - Phi Kappa Phi, 1940-1970 (Box 84)
        [SR RESTRICTED until Jan. 1, 2017 ]
      - Placement Office, 1969-1986 (Box 54)
      - Public Health, School of, 1950-1967 (Box 54)
      - Purdue University, 1952-1985 (Box 54)
      - Questionnaires, 1968-1986 (Box 54)
      - Radiation Laboratory, 1957-1975 (Box 54)
      - Ragone, Dean David V., 1972-1980 (Box 54)
      - Recommended Machine Tools for the Instrument Shop, 1955 (Box 54)
      - Special Committee on Undergraduate Programs, 1960-1970 (Box 54)
      - Speeches by Dean Ragone, 1972-1976 (Box 54)
      - State Budget Request, 1985 (Box 54)
      - "State of the College", 1985 (Box 54)
      - Systems Engineering Program Discussion, 1967 (Box 54)
      - Tellurometer, 1962 (Box 54)
      - Transportation Institute, 1951-1976 (Box 54)
      - Tuskeegee Institute Exchange, 1964-1969 (Box 54)
      - UMTRI (UM Transportation Research Institute), 1965-1986 (Box 55)
      - Undergraduate Engineering Education, 1965 (Box 55)
      - Undergraduate Programs in Computers, 1970-1970 (Box 55)
      - Unions, 1968-1969 (Box 84)
      - U.S. Air Force R.O.T.C., 1949-1953 (Box 55)
      - U.S. Navy, 1967-1970 (Box 55)
      - Waldenwoods Retreat, 1970-1971; 2 folders (Box 55)
      - Walter E. Lay Automotive Laboratory, 1957-1976 (Box 55)
      - Water Resources, 1965-1985 (Box 55)
      - Wayne State University, 1953-1984 (Box 55)
      - Williams, Dean Robert L., 1955-1968 (Box 55)
      - Willow Run Airport, 1945-1968 (Box 55)
    - Deans' Departmental Files
      The Deans' Departmental Files (.5 linear feet) document the involvement of the dean's office in departmental administration and planning. For some departments, this material dates as far back as the 1950s, however the documentation is most comprehensive for the 1970s and 1980s.
      - Aerospace Engineering, 1954-1988 (Box 55)
      - Atmospheric and Oceanic Science, 1982-1990 (Box 55)
      - Bioengineering, 1985 (Box 55)
      - Chemical Engineering, 1981-1987 (Box 55)
      - Chemistry, 1984 (Box 55)
      - Civil Engineering, 1980-1987 (Box 55)
      - Computer, Information and Control Engineering (CICE), 1980-1983 (Box 55)
      - Electrical and Computer Engineering (ECE), 1977-1980; 2 folders (Box 55)
      - Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, 1981-1985 (Box 55)
      - Engineering Physics, 1980-1989 (Box 55)
      - Humanities, 1978-1991 (Box 55)
      - Industrial and Operations, 1977-1985 (Box 55)
      - Materials Science and Engineering, 1971-1989 (Box 55)
      - Mechanical Engineering, 1964-1978 (Box 55)
      - Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics (MEAM), 1979-1985 (Box 56)
      - Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering (NAME), 1964-1987; 2 folders (Box 56)
      - Nuclear Engineering, 1977-1989; 2 folders (Box 56)
  - James J. Duderstadt Files, 1981-1985
    The James J. Duderstadt subseries (2.7 linear feet) provides some sense of his administrative duties and concerns as dean (1981-1986). Some of the major issues which are documented here are the response of the college to advances in computer and other technologies; efforts to encourage a more diverse student body; construction plans on North Campus; and coping with funding problems.
    - Topical File
      - Admissions, 1983 (Box 56)
      - Bioengineering, 1985 (Box 56)
      - Budget, 1981-1984; 2 folders (Box 56)
      - Budget Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 56)
      - Caltech Visit, 1984 (Box 56)
      - Chemical Engineering Chair Search Committee, 1985 (Box 84)
      - Civil Engineering Chairman Search, 1983 (Box 84)
      - Computer and Control Engineering (CICE) and Electrical and Computer Engineering (ECE) Proposal, 1983 (Box 56)
      - Computer Position Search (Box 84)
      - Computers, 1983-1985 (Box 56)
      - Continuing Education for Women, 1983-1984 (Box 56)
      - Control Systems Coordinating Committee, 1984-1985 (Box 56)
      - Dean's Agenda, 1981 (Box 56)
      - Defense Research, 1984-1985 (Box 56)
      - Departmental Reviews, 1981 (Box 56)
      - EDS (Electronic Data Systems Corp.), 1985 (Box 56)
      - EE and CS (Electrical Engineering and Computer Science) Merger, 1983-1985 (Box 56)
      - Electron Microbeam Telescope, 1983-1985 (Box 57)
      - Energy Policy Committee, 1984-1985 (Box 57)
      - Engineering Building I, 1982-1984; 5 folders (Box 57)
      - Engineering-Mathematics-Statistics-Physics Committee, 1983-1984 (Box 57)
      - Engineering Research Center Proposal, 1985 (Box 57)
      - Engineering Student Services, 1983-1985 (Box 57)
      - External Relations Program, 1982-1983 (Box 57)
      - Foreign Visitors, 1983 (Box 57)
      - Form Letters and Memoranda, 1981-1983 (Box 57)
      - Freshman Admissions Summaries, 1982-1983 (Box 57)
      - General Motors Institute, 1981 (Box 57)
      - Harden, Elaine (Assistant to JJD), Administrative Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 57)
      - Humanities Departmental Review, 1982-1984; 2 folders (Box 84)
      - Industrial Technology Institute, 1983 (Box 58)
      - Instructional Television, 1983-1985 (Box 58)
      - Machine Intelligence Program, 1985 (Box 58)
      - Management Incentives, 1984-1985 (Box 58)
      - Materials and Metallurgical Science Chairman Search, 1983 (Box 84)
      - Math "Hit and Run" Committee, 1984-1985 (Box 58)
      - Michigan Project on Industry-University Cooperation, 1984-1985 (Box 58)
      - Michigan Society of Professional Engineers, 1984-1985 (Box 58)
      - Michigan Technology Council, 1984-1985 (Box 58)
      - National Alumni Advisory Committee, 1981-1985; 2 folders (Box 58)
      - North Campus Instructional Complex, 1983-1985 (Box 58)
      - North Campus Move, 1982-1983 (Box 58)
      - Nuclear Engineering Review, 1983-1984 (Box 58)
      - Placement Office Review, 1984-1985 (Box 58)
      - Program Revision Request, 1981 (Box 58)
      - Quantum Engineering, 1983-1984 (Box 58)
      - "Radiation Transport in Dense Plasma" (with S. Freije), 1981 (Box 58)
      - Research, 1981-1985; 2 folders (Box 58)
      - Resource Allocation, 1981-1982 (Box 58)
      - Software Engineering Institute, 1984 (Box 58)
      - Space Physics Research Laboratory, 1984-1985 (Box 58)
      - Standing Faculty Committee Minutes, 1983-1985 (Box 58)
      - Strategic Defense Initiative (SDI), 1985 (Box 59)
      - Supercomputers, 1983-1985; 2 folders (Box 59)
      - Talks, 1983-1985 (Box 59)
      - Texas A&M Review, 1983 (Box 59)
      - UM Academic Affairs Advisory Council, 1983-1984 (Box 59)
      - Washington Testimony, 1985 (Box 59)
    - Subject Files
      - Budget Report, 1982-1983 (Box 93)
      - College of Engineering Annual Report, 1983-1984 (Box 93)
      - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 93)
      - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 93)
      - Dean's Report
        - Outline and Preface (Box 93)
        - Mission 1.0-2.0 (Box 93)
        - Enrollment Status 3.0-3.2, 3.3-4 (Box 93)
        - Faculty Status 3.4 (Box 93)
        - Alumni 3.5 (Box 93)
        - Facilities, 3.7 (Box 93)
        - University Comparisons 3.8-3.9 (Box 93)
        - Quality 4.0-4.5 (Box 93)
        - Instruction 5.0 (Box 93)
        - Research 6.0 (Box 93)
        - Industry 7.0 (Box 93)
        - Private Support 8.0 (Box 93)
        - Priorities 9.0 (Box 93)
      - Enrollment Statistics (ca. 1984) (Box 93)
      - Organizational Chart (not dated) (Box 93)
      - Presentations, 1985 (Box 93)
      - State of the University of Michigan College of Engineering, 1985 (Box 93)
      - Three-year Status Report, 1981 (Box 93)
      - Report on Engineering Education At Michigan: Crisis, Challenge, and Opportunity, 1982 (Box 93)
      - Report on Undergraduate Engineering Education, 1985 (Box 93)
      - Salary Surveys, 1984 (Box 93)
      - Status Report: Five-Year Budget Plan, 1982 (Box 93)
- Associate Dean's Files, 1980-1992
  The Associate Dean's Files (10 linear feet) are divided into five subseries: Chronological Files of Charles Vest; Senior Associate Dean's Files, 1980-1992; and Project Files of Daniel E. Atkins, 1981-1989, H.F. Fogler Files and M. J. Sinnott Files.
  The series Chronological Files of Charles Vest is arranged chronologically and covers the years 1981 to 1988. These files contain both personal and administrative records and reflect Vest's personal areas of research interest and knowledge. Correspondence with colleagues and reviews for journals of the work of other professionals comprise the bulk of the material. The closed folder contains his evaluations of doctoral dissertations. Additional files of Charles vest were received in the 1992 accession, boxes 61-62.
  - Chronological Files of Charles Vest
    - 1983 (Box 43)
    - 1984-1988, 4 folders (Box 43)
    - 1984-1988, 1 folders (Box 51)
    - Correspondence, chronological, 1981-1984; 5 folders (Box 61)
    - Correspondence, chronological, 1984; 8 folders (Box 62)
  - Senior Associate Dean's Files
    After Peter M. Banks became the dean of the College of Engineering in 1990, the position of Senior Associate Dean was created. Erdogan Gulari, formerly the Associate Dean for Academic Affairs, was appointed to this position. In addition, the positions of Associate Dean of Graduate Education and Associate Dean of Research and Undergraduate Education were also created, thereby relieving the senior associate dean of student concerns and allowing Gulari to focus on departmental issues and faculty development. (This reorganization is not documented within the records.) The subseries Senior Associate Dean's Files, 1980-1992 includes Gulari's files from his years as Associate Dean for Academic Affairs as well as his files from his first years as Senior Associate Dean.
    The Senior Associate Dean's Files, 1980-1992 subseries is sub-divided into Departmental Files and Administrative Files. The Departmental Files are a valuable source of information regarding the research emphases of the various departments during the 1980s and includes such forms of documentation as departmental reviews and faculty appointments. For earlier information regarding departmental activities, the researcher should refer to the department files scattered throughout the DEAN'S FILES series (see especially Ivan C. Crawford and Successors' Topical Files subseries). Budget materials for the individual departments are located in the Administrative Files. Issues relating to students are also represented in the Administrative Files in such folders as "Affirmative Action and Racism Issues", "Enrollment", "Graduate Students", and "Minority Engineering Program Office".
    - Departmental Files
      - Aerospace Engineering
        - General, 1983-1989; 2 folders (Box 44)
        - Grievances, 1988 (Box 51)
          [SR RESTRICTED until Jan. 1, 2063 ]
        - Promotions and Tenure, 1983; 1986 (Box 51)
        - Strategic Defense Initiative, 1985-1986 (Box 44)
      - Atmospheric, Oceanic and Space Sciences
        - General, 1985-1989; 2 folders (Box 44)
        - Appointments, 1986-1989; 2 folders (Box 44)
          - 1986-1989 (Box 44)
          - 1986-1989 (Box 51)
        - Oceanography (transfer to Department of Geological Sciences), 1986-1987 (Box 44)
        - Promotions, Tenure, and Reappointments, 1985-1989; 2 folders (Box 51)
        - Review, 1988-1990 (Box 44)
      - Bioengineering Program
        - General, 1980-1989 (Box 44)
        - Chair Search, 1985-1989; 3 folders (Box 51)
          [CLOSED until Jan. 1, 2019 ]
        - Review, 1985 (Box 44)
      - Chemical Engineering
        - General, 1986-1987 (Box 44)
        - Appointments, 1987-1989 (Box 44)
        - Cell Culture Facility, 1985-1987 (Box 44)
        - Chair Search, 1985 (Box 51)
        - Engineering 103, 1986-1988 (Box 44)
        - Promotions and Tenure, 1986-1987 (Box 51)
        - Review, 1989 (Box 44)
      - Civil Engineering
        - General, 1986-1987 (Box 44)
        - Appointments, 1986-1989; 2 folders (Box 44)
        - Minority Fellowship Aid, 1987 (Box 51)
        - Promotions and Tenure, 1982-1986 (Box 51)
        - Retirements, 1985 (Box 51)
      - Electrical Engineering and Computer Science
        - General, 1986-1989; 4 folders (Box 44)
        - Promotions, Tenure, and Reappointments, 1987 (Box 51)
        - Requests, 1986-1989 (Box 44)
        - Review, 1986 (Box 44)
        - Solid-State Electronics Laboratory, 1986-1989 (Box 44)
        - Students, 1988 (Box 51)
      - Humanities Program
        - Appointments, 1989 (Box 44)
        - Appointments, 1989 (Box 51)
        - Retirements, 1990 (Box 51)
          [PR RESTRICTED until Jan. 1, 2020 ]
      - Industrial and Operations Engineering
        - Anderson Chair Candidate Search, 1985-1986 (Box 51)
        - Requests, 1988-1989 (Box 44)
        - Review, 1986 (Box 44)
      - Macromolecular Science and Engineering Program, 1988 (Box 44)
      - Materials Science and Engineering
        - General, 1986-1987 (Box 44)
        - Appointments and Recruitment, 1986-1987 (Box 51)
          [PR RESTRICTED until Jan. 1, 2062 ]
        - Electron Microbeam Analysis Laboratory (EMAL)
          - General, 1986-1991; 2 folders (Box 44)
          - Executive Committee, 1986 (Box 44)
        - Requests, 1986; 1989 (Box 44)
        - Retirements, 1989 (Box 51)
      - Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics
        - General, 1987-1988 (Box 45)
        - Review, 1987 (Box 45)
      - Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering
        - Department Name Change, 1987 (Box 45)
        - Faculty Resumes, 1988-1989 (Box 45)
        - Offshore Engineering, The University of Michigan/ Sea Grant/ Industry Consortium in, 1989 (Box 45)
      - Nuclear Engineering
        - General, 1986-1989 (Box 45)
        - Chair Search, 1989 (Box 51)
        - Imaging, 1987 (Box 45)
        - Requests, 1988-1990 (Box 45)
    - Administrative Files
      - Accreditation Board for Engineering and Technology (ABET)
        - General, 1988-1989 (Box 45)
        - Engineering Accreditation Commission, 1988 (Box 45)
        - Review of Engineering Programs, 1984-1985; 2 folders (Box 45)
      - Advanced Computer Architecture Laboratory (ACAL), 1986-1989 (Box 45)
      - Affirmative Action and Racism Issues, 1987 (Box 45)
      - Applied Physics Program
        - General, 1987-1989 (Box 45)
        - Search Committee, 1988-1989 (Box 51)
      - Budget
        - General, 1988-1989; 2 folders (Box 45)
        - General Fund Budget History, 1981-1988 (Box 45)
        - Aerospace Engineering, Department of, 1986-1989 (Box 45)
        - Atmospheric, Oceanic and Space Sciences, Department of, 1987-1988 (Box 45)
        - Chemical Engineering, Department of, 1987-1989 (Box 45)
        - Civil Engineering, Department of, 1987-1989 (Box 45)
        - Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, Department of, 1987-1989 (Box 45)
        - Humanities Program
          - General, 1987-1989; 2 folders (Box 45)
          - Course Evaluations
            - Humanities 430 Winter, 1988 (Box 45)
            - Humanities 432 Fall, 1987 (Box 45)
            - Humanities 440
              - Fall, 1987 (Box 45)
              - Winter, 1988 (Box 45)
        - Industrial and Operations Engineering, Department of, 1987-1989 (Box 45)
        - Information Technology, 1988-1989 (Box 45)
        - Materials Science and Engineering, Department of, 1987-1989 (Box 45)
        - Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics, Department of, 1987-1989 (Box 45)
        - Michigan Engineering and Television Network, 1986-1987 (Box 45)
        - Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering, Department of, 1987-1989 (Box 45)
        - Nuclear Engineering, Department of, 1987-1989 (Box 45)
        - Robotics and Integrated Management, Center for (CRIM), 1988-1989 (Box 45)
        - Technical Communications, 1987-1989 (Box 45)
      - Cellular Bioengineering, Center for, 1987 (Box 45)
      - Child Care Center Survey Responses, 1988 (Box 45)
      - Departmental Reviews, 1988 (Box 45)
      - Engineering Library Committee, 1988-1989 (Box 45)
      - Engineering Summer Conferences, 1987-1988 (Box 45)
      - Enrollment, 1972/73-1988/89
        - 1972/73-1988/89, 9 folders (Box 46)
        - 1987/88 (Box 51)
      - Exchanges
        - Hiroshima University, 1989 (Box 46)
        - The Technical University of Berlin, 1989 (Box 46)
      - Faculty
        - Faculty Development
          - General, 1989 (Box 46)
          - Faculty Development Fund, 1987 (Box 46)
        - Faculty Headcount, 1987-1989 (Box 46)
        - Faculty Meeting, April 5, 1988 (Box 46)
        - Faculty Rules, 1986; 1988 (Box 46)
        - Salaries, 1988-1989 (Box 46)
      - General Motors, 1985-1987 (Box 46)
      - Graduate Students
        - Research Assistants and Teaching Assistants, 1987-1989; 2 folders (Box 46)
        - Support Issues, 1988 (Box 46)
      - History Timeline (Box 46)
      - Hunting Licenses, 1986-1989; 2 folders (Box 51)
      - Minority Engineering Program Office (MEPO)
        - General, 1988-1989; 2 folders (Box 51)
          [SR RESTRICTED until Jan. 1, 2064 ]
        - Budget Outline, 1987-1988 (Box 46)
        - Professionals-In-Training Program, Final Report, 1989 (Box 46)
        - Select Student Support Services Project, Final Reports, 1988-1989; 2 folders (Box 46)
      - NASA Proposals, 1987
        - Peer Data, 1987-1988 (Box 46)
        - Robotics Research Laboratory, 1988 (Box 46)
        - Science and Technology, Institute of, 1987-1992 (Box 46)
        - Science Development Council, 1988-1989; 3 folders (Box 46)
      - Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, Department of
        - General, 1984-1986 (Box 46)
        - Computer and Communication Sciences, Department of (LS&A)
          - Chair Search Committee, 1980-1981 (Box 51)
          - Review, External, 1980 (Box 46)
        - Computer, Information and Control Engineering Program, Review, Internal, 1983 (Box 46)
        - Computer Science and Engineering, Division of 1981-1983, undated (re: establishment), 3 folders (Box 46)
        - Computer Science Instruction, Committee on, 1982 (Box 46)
        - Review, External, 1985 (Box 46)
      - Industrial Technology Institute (ITI) (Box 48)
        - General, 1982-1983 (Box 48)
        - Board of Directors (presentation),1983 February (Box 48)
        - Director Search, 1982 (Box 51)
        - Information and Communication System, 1983 (Box 48)
        - Location, 1982-1983 (Box 48)
        - Proposal (re: establishment), 1981-1982 (Box 48)
        - Relationship with Other Universities, 1982-1983 (Box 48)
      - Provost Search Advisory Committee, 1988; 2 folders (Box 48)
      - Robotics and Integrated Manufacturing, Center for (CRIM)
        - General, 1981-1983; 2 folders (Box 48)
        - Air Force Office of Scientific Research (AFOSR) (site visit), 1982 (Box 48)
        - Budget, 1981-1983 (Box 49)
        - Datsko, Joseph (research materials), undated (Box 49)
        - Faculty Research Interests, 1980-1981; undated (Box 49)
        - Industrial Technology Institute (ITI) and CRIM
          - Recruiting, 1982-1983 (Box 51)
          - Relationship between ITI and CRIM, 1981-1982 (Box 49)
          - Seminar Series, 1981-1983 (Box 49)
        - Integrated Design and Manufacturing Division
          - General, 1981-1982 (Box 49)
          - Director Search, 1982 (Box 51)
          - Statements of Research Activities, 1982 (Box 49)
        - Management Systems Division
          - General, 1982-1983 (Box 49)
          - Leadership, 1982 (Box 51)
        - Manufacturing Research and Instruction, A Proposal to the General Electric Company for the Support of, 1983 (Box 49)
        - Michigan Energy and Resource Research Association (MERRA); Manufacturing Education Center Proposal, 1982 (Box 49)
        - Newsclippings and Press Releases, 1981-1982 (Box 49)
        - Robotics and Integrated Manufacturing, Coordinated Research in (proposal), 1981 (Box 49)
        - Robotics Systems Division
          - General, 1981-1983 (Box 49)
          - Robotics Industrial Affiliates Program, 1981-1983 (Box 49)
          - Statements of Research Activities, 1982 (Box 49)
        - Steering Committee Meeting Minutes, 1981-1982 (Box 49)
      - Science and Technology, Institute of
        - General, 1982-1991 (Box 49)
        - Reviews and Evaluations, 1978; 1984-1987 (Box 49)
  - Project Files of Dan Atkins
    The Project Files of Daniel E. Atkins, 1981-1989 subseries reflects some of the major projects of the College of Engineering in which Atkins was involved, and include material created during his tenure as Associate Dean for Research and Graduate Programs. The files are divided into six sections. The section "Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science" documents the merger of academic computing units at the university into one department within the College of Engineering and includes reviews from various years. The section "Experimental Research in Electronic Submission Project", or EXPRES, traces the evolution of the project from its initial funding by the National Science Foundation (NSF) in 1986 to 1989 when NSF discontinued funding. This section is divided into Chronological Files and Topical Files. Both files contain similar types of material, such as research proposals and activity reports; however, the Chronological Files include the meeting minutes of the Advisory Committee.